All these houses are built on garbage
यह जो सारे घर हैं, यह सब कूड़े के ऊपर ही
[music].  There's this
[संगीत]
house and right
हैं। यह एक घर है और इसके ठीक
in front of it is
सामने
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
creek.  This one scene will tell you why
नाला। यह एक दृश्य बता देगा कि क्यों यहां
life expectancy here is half that of the rest of India.  It
लाइफ एक्सपेक्टेंसी आधी है बाकी इंडिया
is the lowest in entire Mumbai.  Here a
से। पूरी मुंबई में सबसे कम है। यहां एक
person cannot live more than 40 years.
इंसान 40 साल से ज्यादा जी नहीं पाता।
handle it
संभाल के
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
our life is a dog.  Do you understand dog
हमारी जिंदगी कुत्ता है। कुत्ता समझते हो
?
ना? जितनी आसानी से नशा मिल जाता है उतनी
Water is not as easily available as intoxicants.
आसानी से पानी नहीं मिलता।
This is the largest dumping ground not only of India but of entire Asia.
ये इंडिया का ही नहीं पूरी एशिया का
This is also India's
लार्जेस्ट डंपिंग ग्राउंड। ये इंडिया का
oldest dumping ground.
ओल्डेस्ट डंपिंग ग्राउंड भी है।
Built during the British period, today it is
ब्रिटिश टाइम में बना आज ये 200 फुटबॉल
bigger than 200 football fields.  This is our
फील्ड से भी ज्यादा बड़ा है। यह है हमारे
Mumbai's Danar dumping
मुंबई का दनार डंपिंग
ground which is also home to 2 lakh people.
ग्राउंड जो 2 लाख लोगों का घर भी है।
All the houses here are made of blue tin which
यहां के हर घर यह ब्लू टिन से बने हैं जो
can break at any time and
कभी भी टूट सकते हैं और बारिश के वक्त यह
also leaks during rain.  The rooms in these houses are
टपकते भी हैं। इन घरों के कमरे हैं तो
very small but in many houses up to six to seven people
बहुत छोटे लेकिन कई घरों में छह सात लोग
live.
तक रहते
Most of the people here
हैं। यहां ज्यादातर लोग कपड़ों में शीशे
work in attaching glass to clothes.  Children also
लगाने का काम करते हैं। बच्चे भी इसमें हर
get Rs. 6 to 8 for each piece of clothing.
एक कपड़े का उन्हें कुछ छ से आठ मिलते
[Music]
[संगीत]
Somewhere here the road itself has become a drain.  Meaning, the
यहां कहीं रोड ही नाला बन चुकी है। मतलब
dirty water from the gutter has come on the road.  That's why
गटर का गंदा पानी रोड पर आ चुका है। इसलिए
people have built a road here by installing wooden doors.
लोगों ने लकड़ी दरवाजे लगा के यहां पर रोड
People coming and going face trouble.
बनाई है। आने जाने वाले को तकलीफ होता है।
We people also suffer.  Water
हम लोग को भी तकलीफ होता है। पानी चारों
is filled all around.  Where should the man come
तरफ से भरा रहता है। आदमी आए जाए कि किधर
from?
से?
Everybody gets hurt.  Be it big or small.  The
सबको तकलीफ होता है। चाहे बड़ा हो या छोटा
children face the most problems
हो। बच्चों को सब सबसे ज्यादा तकलीफ तो
because they have to go to and come from school.
बच्चे लोग का है क्योंकि वो उनको स्कूल
My leg has been bad since I was one and a half years old.
मैं डेढ़ साल की तब से मेरा पैर खराब हो
What happened, tell me, if it happened because of polio,
चुका है। क्या हुआ बता पोलियो पोलियो से
what difficulties does a handicapped person face? It is very
इंसान को की क्या मुश्किलें होती है बहुत
difficult to walk, look at the pipes,
मुश्किल होती है चलने की देखो पाइप देखिए
look at the dirt, you can see the dirt and
गंदगी देखिए ना आप गंदगी दिख सकती है और
insects keep crawling around, there are a lot of holes here, there is a dug pit, there are a
कीड़े मकोड़े ऐसा रेंगते रहते हैं यहां पे
lot of problems here and I have also fallen many times,
ऐसे बहुत परेशानी है और मैं भी कई बार गिर
look, the gutter is broken,
चुकी हूं देखो गटर टूट भी गई है गिरने के
my brother has also fallen after falling
बाद मेरे भाई भी गिर चुके हैं
[Music]
[संगीत]
and was this always a drain or was it ever clean
और ये हमेशा से नाला था या ये कभी साफ भी
?  This was very clean.  This was very clear water.
था? ये बहुत क्लीन था। ये बहुत साफ पानी
I have told you earlier also that two big
था। मैंने इससे पहले भी बताया कि दो बड़ी
boats and ships used to go together.  Now there is
नाव शिप एक साथ जाती थी। अब सिर्फ कचरे के
nothing left here except garbage.   There
अलावा कुछ नहीं बचा यहां पे।
is a problem of drug addiction here.  The
नशे की प्रॉब्लम है यहां पे। बहुत सबसे
biggest problem is drug addiction, and
ज्यादा प्रॉब्लम तो नशे नशे की है और नशे
crime is caused by drug addiction.  There are more intoxicants here than the number of castes.
से ही क्राइम है। यहां पे जितनी जातियां
Ganja, Sulli
गांजा सुल्ली
drugs, even white drugs have reached here.  The
ड्रग्स वाइट वाला ड्रग्स तक यहां पे पहुंच
only problem is addiction.  If you do
गया है। बस सिर्फ नशे की परेशानी है। नशा
n't take drugs, you will talk nicely.  I
नहीं करेगा तो बातों अच्छे करेंगे। काम
will go to work.  If you remain famous for your addiction,
धंधे पे जाएंगे। नशा में मशहूर रहेंगे तो
where will you find work?  Where will he talk properly
कहां काम दिखेगा? कहां वो बात अच्छा से
?  What happened to the eye?  Our
करेंगे? क्या हुआ आंख में? वही हमारा
old man got into a fight while drunk and lost his eye.  The
बुड्ढा नशा में फाइट मार दिया तो आंख खत्म
man broke his eye while drunk.
हो गया। आदमी ने नशे में आंख तोड़ दिया।
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
People pass through this dirty drain water every day.
इसी गंदे नाले के पानी से लोग रोज गुजरते
Children play in it.  There are flies.
हैं। बच्चे इसमें खेलते हैं। मक्खियां
So it is justified.  It is obvious that
होती है। तो जायज है। मतलब ऑब्वियस है कि
people suffer from many diseases too.
लोगों को बीमारियां भी बहुत ही होती हैं।
[Music]
[संगीत]
One day in his childhood he had a fever so he went to a doctor and
एक दिन बुखार आया बचपन में तो एक डॉक्टर
the doctor
के पास आके गए तो उस डॉक्टर ने इंजेक्शन
gave him an injection of polio. Because of that his leg got damaged and he was
दे दी पोलियो की हम तो उससे पैर खराब हो
not able to walk the next day. So the
गया तो अगले दिन चल नहीं पा रहा था तो
police took him to jail, that is the police took him to the
उसको पुलिस पुलिस मतलब जेल में लेके चली
doctor and said to him that until this child gets
गई डॉक्टर को हां और बोले जब तक ये बच्चा
well, he will remain in jail.
सही नहीं तब तक जेल में रहोगे।
Greetings.
अस्सलाम वालेकुम।
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
Water is a great illusion.
पानी का तो बहुत बड़ा भ्रम होता है।
Sometimes water doesn't even come.  It comes dirty.
कभी-कभी आता भी नहीं है पानी। गंदा आता
red Yellow.  Yes, red and yellow water comes.
है। लाल पीला। हां, लाल पीला पानी आता है।
Red yellow water.  Drinking water comes to homes through these pipes.
लाल पीला पानी। इन पाइप से घरों में पीने
Just two hours every day.  But
का पानी आता है। रोज दो घंटे बस। लेकिन
these pipes are attached to the gutter drain.
यही पाइप्स गटर के नाले के साथ लगी है।
[MUSIC] It's
[संगीत]
so expensive.  In some days it
इतनी महंगाई हो गई है। कुछ दिनों में ऐसा
seems that
भी लगता है कि पेट्रोल के भाव में पानी
in this area, water will be available at the price of petrol.  what do you do
मिलने वाला है इस एरिया में। आप क्या करते
by the way sir?  I do sewing work.   I
हैं वैसे सर? मैं सिलाई का काम करता हूं।
work as a labourer.  Sometimes it happens that one has to
मजदूरी करता हूं। कभी-कभी ऐसा होता है कि
go to the company and take a bath.
उधर ही कंपनी में जाके नहाना रहता है। इधर
Because there is no water here.
पानी नहीं रहने की वजह से। ऐसी जगहों की
Udu, an all in one business platform
है उडू जो एक ऑल इन वन बिनेस प्लेटफार्म
with 45 plus apps, helps us in bringing the stories of such places to you.  With this, I created
है विद 45 प्लस एप्स। इसी से मैंने बनाई
my website and that too for free in just 30
अपनी वेबसाइट वो भी फ्री में सिर्फ 30
minutes.  It doesn't have a website builder
मिनट्स में। इसमें ना एक वेबसाइट बिल्डर
app.  Choose your website type in this.
ऐप है। इसमें अपना वेबसाइट टाइप चूज़ करो।
Like I had to make a business website and
जैसे मुझे एक बिजनेस वेबसाइट बनानी थी और
my business is infotainment.  Then I
मेरा बिज़नेस इंफोटेनमेंट है। फिर मैंने
selected the objective develop a brand.
सेलेक्ट किया ऑब्जेक्टिव डेवलप अ ब्रांड।
Now from this color palette I selected colors for my website.
अब इस कलर पैेट से मैंने अपनी वेबसाइट के
Or simply
लिए कलर्स सेलेक्ट कर लिए। या सिंपली
I uploaded my brand logo and
मैंने अपना ब्रांड लोगो अपलोड किया जिससे
got its color palette.  Then
मेरे को उसका कलर पैेट मिल गया। फिर जो भी
I selected whatever pages I needed.  Selected a
पेजेस चाहिए वो मैंने सेलेक्ट किए। इतनी
suitable theme from so many AI generated themes.
सारी एआई जनरेटेड थीम्स में से सूटेबल थीम
All the work is done with easy drag and drop.  Like creating columns,
सारा काम हो जाता है। जैसे कॉलम्स बनाना,
changing photos and text.  I
फोटोस और टेक्स्ट चेंज करना। मैं एआई से
can have AI generate text.  I
टेक्स्ट जनरेट करवा सकती हूं। इवन न्यू
can even add new pages easily.  See how
पेजेस डाल सकती हूं इजीली। देखा कितनी
easily a website is developed.  So the
आसानी से एक वेबसाइट डेवलप हो जाती है। तो
link to Udoo's website builder is
उडू के वेबसाइट बिल्डर का लिंक नीचे
in the description below.  Check it out now.
डिस्क्रिप्शन में है। अभी इसे चेक आउट
Now let's go back to the video.  Even today
करो। अब चलते हैं वापस वीडियो पे। आज भी
madam I beg.  So this house of
मैडम मैं भीख मांगती हूं। तो ये घर भी
mine is also built with donations.  What is your definition of a home
मेरा चंदे में बना है। आपके लिए एक घर की
?  What is home? Home  The big
परिभाषा क्या रहेगी? घर क्या है घर? बड़े
people are rich.  He has a very
लोग जो है पैसे वाले हैं। उनका सपना बहुत
big dream.  Our dream is small.  The
बड़ा है। हमारा सपना छोटा है। 2004 में
rooms were broken in 2004, so our fight started in 2004.
रूम टूटे थे तो 2004 में हमारी लड़ाई चालू
That's what I want to say brother.  If
हुई थी। मेरा वही बोलना है भाई। अगर जो
you want to destroy something, ruin the poor, then
तुझे तोड़ना है, गरीबों को उजाड़ना है तो
first kill the poor.  Anyway they are lying
सबसे पहले गरीबों को मार दे। वैसे भी तो
dead
मरे पड़े हैं
[music]
[संगीत]
poor people and these mosquitoes, because of mosquitoes I have to get
गरीब और ये मच्छर है ना मच्छर के वजह से
admitted in the hospital every ten days
मेरे को 10 दिन में एडमिट होना पड़ता है
because mosquitoes bite and I get
दवाखाने में क्योंकि मच्छर काटता है
typhoid and malaria, why are you always crying,
टाइफाइड मलेरिया हो जाता है मुझे हमेशा रो
you mean you are alone like this, I am alone, I have a
क्यों रही है आप मतलब ऐसा है अकेली ऐसा है
disease, and I had a son, he
ना अकेली हूं बीमारी है और एक बेटा था वो
died by hanging himself, he was young
फांसी लगा के मर गया छोटा था
and whatever he has, he is within himself.  We have God
और जो है वह अपने में है। हमको ऊपर वाला
and you people.  Nothing else,
है और आप लोग हैं। बस और कुछ नहीं
son.  Come on son, this is my house.  Poor food.
बेटा। आओ बेटा ये मेरा घर है। गरीब खाना।
This is a house which is home to the Danar dumping ground.  My
यह है एक घर जो दनार डंपिंग ग्राउंड का घर
aunt lives here.  She lives alone.  She
है। यहीं पे खाला रहती हैं। अकेले रहती
cooks food.  Here,
है। खाना बनाती हैं। यहां पर बर्तन में
water is kept in a vessel.  There is a place for urinating here
पानी रखती हैं। यहां पर पेशाब का जगह है
and this room gets filled with water during the rainy season.
और यही कमरा बरसात के वक्त पानी से भर
This is the first time that we turned on the camera
ऐसा पहली बार हुआ है कि हमने कैमरा ऑन
and as soon as we did it, tears started flowing from the person's eyes.
किया और ऑन करते ही इंसान की आंखों से
This shows that no
आंसू आने लग गए। ये बताता है कि उनकी बात
one ever listened to him, neither his family nor the
कभी किसी ने सुनी नहीं, ना परिवार ने
country.  Then you will say
सुनी, ना देश ने सुनी। फिर आप बोलोगे कि
why do you make videos in such streets, in such places
ऐसी गलियों में, ऐसी जगहों में क्यों
?  This is dirty.  But are the
वीडियो बनाते हो? यह तो गंदी है। पर क्या
people living here not humans?  These streets have
यहां रहने वाले लोग इंसान नहीं? इन गलियों
provided home to many people from India.
ने घर दिया है भारत से आए बहुत सारे लोगों
But these same streets tell us that Mumbai
को। लेकिन यही गलियां बताती हैं कि मुंबई
is a city that takes
वो शहर है
away much more from us than what it gives.   There
छीन भी लेता है।
is an addiction in it, there is the addiction
इसमें नशा है इसमें नशा है वाइटनर
of whitener, this whitener addiction and many such addictions will be found in
का ये वाइटनर नशा और कई सारे ऐसे नशे इन
abundance in these streets, in this area
गलियों में इस एरिया में पूरे बहुत
and many people will be found doing it as well,
मिलेंगे और बहुत लोग करते हुए भी मिलेंगे
when did you start doing it, it's
कब से करना शुरू किया आपने मैं हो हो गया
been 10-12 years.  Well since last 10-12 years
10 12 साल हो गए। अच्छा 10 12 साल से कर
we are addicted to only whitener or nothing
रहे हैं हम नशा सिर्फ वाइटनर का ही या फिर
else, how much does it cost to get only whitener
और भी नहीं सिर्फ वाइटनर कितने की मिलती
?
है ये?
For ₹60.  506 for ₹60 and how much does it cost?
₹60 की। ₹60 की 506 और कितनी चलती है ये?
It lasts for 3-4 hours.  How much do you take
ये तीन-4 घंटा चलती है। कितनी लेते हो एक
in a day?  One or two times at the most,
दिन में? एक से दो बार बहुत
₹120 is spent on the bottle every day.  Yes.
तो ₹120 का हर दिन बोतल में जाता है। हां।
Yes, gutkhavak in a bottle for ₹100
हां ₹100 बोतल में गुटकावटका
and mother says that yours
और अम्मा बोलती है आपकी ये छोड़ने को
asks me to quit, she beats me for drugs,
बोलती है अरे मारती मेरे को नशे के लिए
all the family members shout at me, I beat her, I ca
मारती है सब घर वाले चिल्लाते हैं मारते
n't stop myself now, yes I don't hide, I
छूटता नहीं है अब हां छुपता नहीं कोशिश की
try, after a day or two, I
कोशिश करता हूं तो एक आध दिन बाद उसके बाद
take my hand back like that,
ले लेता हाथ
well it is clear here that living here is
अच्छा यहां ये तो साफ है कि यहां रहना
deadly and dangerous.  But the irony is
डेडली और डेंजरस है। लेकिन आयरन ही ये है
that the government has decided that out of the
कि सरकार ने ये डिसाइड किया है कि यहां का
300 acre mountain here, half of it, i.e.
जो 300 एकड़ का पहाड़ है उसमें आधा यानी
124 acres, will be cleared and the
124 एकड़ को साफ करके यहां पे धारावी यानी
people of Dharavi, i.e. other slums, will be sent here.  Meaning,
दूसरे स्लम के लोगों को भेजेंगे। मतलब
instead of removing people from here, they will
यहां से लोगों को हटाने की बजाय और लोगों
bring more people here and put them in danger.
को लाके खतरे में डालेंगे।
This garbage is 40 meters high, which is more than a 12-
यह जो कूड़ा है ना यह 40 मीटर यानी एक 12
storey building, and it
मंजिल बिल्डिंग से भी ज्यादा ऊंचा है जिसे
might take 12 to 14 years to clean it
साफ करने में 12 से 14 साल लग सकते
[Music].
[संगीत]
In this mountain, you will find wet and dry waste together,
हैं। इस पहाड़ में गीला सूखा कचरा साथ में
which people segregate and sell to
मिलेगा जिसे सेग्रगेट करके लोग बेच के
earn Rs. 1200.  But this work is not easy.
₹1200 कमाते हैं। लेकिन यह काम आसान नहीं।
Many people have lost their lives doing this.
यही करने में कई लोगों ने जान गवाई है।
Some people have even come under the bulldozer.  Many
कुछ लोग तो बुलडोजर के नीचे भी आए हैं। कई
people suffered multiple injuries.
लोग बहुत सारी चोटों के शिकार हुए।
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
This is a long tease but my whole leg wo
ये लंबा चिढ़ा दिया लेकिन मेरा पूरा पैर
n't close.  Now the leg doesn't close.
बंद नहीं हो रहा है। अब पैर बंद नहीं
No, it is not stopping completely.  Earlier it would
होता। नहीं पूरा बंद नहीं हो रहा। पहले तो
not stop even for a little while.  Right now,
थोड़ा ही नहीं बंद होता था। अभी इतना ऐसा
say this much is happening.  Yes.  And when did you feel this?  It's done.  It's
बोलो हो रहा है। हां। और ये लगा कब? लगा
been six months.  What were
हो गया। छ महीना हो गया। क्या कर रहे थे
you doing when it happened?  I was working.  He had gone
आप जब लगा? मैं काम कर रहा था। काम पहाड़
to the mountain to count the work.  Yes.  The
में ही गिनने गए थे। हां। बिनने का काम
work of picking.  Yes.  I am not able to work.   I
चुनने का काम। हां। काम नहीं कर पाते ना।
can't walk.  Look, don't fall and break everything.
चल नहीं पाते। देखो गिर के ना फेरमे सब
We think that only
हम सोचते हैं कि ऐसी जगहों में सिर्फ
people from other cities live in such places.  But it
दूसरे शहरों से आकर लोग रहते हैं। पर ऐसा
is not like that.  There are many such communities in Mumbai itself
नहीं है। मुंबई में ही कई सारी ऐसी
which are not accepted by their own family members.
कम्युनिटीज है जिन्हें उनके ही घर वाले
Society does not accept it.  So these
नहीं अपनाते। सोसाइटी नहीं अपनाती। तो ये
houses provide them shelter.  One of them is the
घर उनको छत देते हैं। उनमें से एक है
transgender community of Mumbai.
मुंबई की ट्रांसजेंडर यानी किन्नर
God sent us into this world
कम्युनिटी। दुनिया में भगवान हमको भेजा
just to make us laugh and feel happy.
सिर्फ हंसाने के लिए और हंसमुख करने के
Never sent it to hurt anyone.
लिए। कभी किसी का दिल दुखाने के लिए नहीं
People would chase us away, people would abuse us.
भेजा। लोग हमको भगाते, लोग हमको गाली
People look at me with dirty eyes, I do
देते। लोग हमको गंदी नजर से हम वो सब का
n't care about all that.  We live with the support of just one Allah and one
फिक्र नहीं करते। हम बस एक अल्लाह एक
God, neither people accepted us,
भगवान के सहारे हम जीते ना लोगों ने नहीं
nor any relative, nor brother or sister, then I
ना कोई रिश्तेदार ना भाई बहन तब मैं इनके
came to him, then he supported me,
पास आई तब इन्होंने मेरा सपोर्ट किए मेरी
talked to my family members, so now that you have
फैमिली वालों से बात की तो अब जब आपको एक
got a home, what is the definition of home for you?
घर मिला आपके लिए घर की परिभाषा क्या हुई?
As far as I believe,
घर तो जहां तक मतलब मेरा मानना है हम
for people like us, even our parents' home doesn't exist.
जैसों के लिए मां-बाप का घर भी नहीं होता।
Why?  These things still happen sometimes.
क्यों? अभी भी कभी-कभी यह बातें होती हैं।
Hey, this is a eunuch right?  This will give us some progeny.  If we
अरे यह तो है ना? यह थोड़ी वंश देगा
look at home, this is our home.
हमको। घर देखा जाए तो हमारा घर यही है। ये
All these eunuchs of us are here.  This is who
जितने हम लोग किन्नर हैं यही हम हैं। यही
we are.  This is our home, these are our
हम ही हैं। यही हमारा घर, यही हमारे
parents, this is our support.  understand.  If we
मां-बाप, यही हमारा सहारा। समझो। अगर एक
get even a hut along with a eunuch, it
किन्नरों के साथ एक झोपड़ा भी मिल जाए तो
is a luxurious palace for us.   There are
हमारे लिए एक आलीशान महल है।
many issues here, hence there are people
यहां इश्यूज बहुत हैं तो इसलिए वो लोग भी
who write songs and rap on these issues
हैं जो इन इश्यूज से गाने लिखकर रैप बनाते
and then spread these issues to the entire world.  The
हैं और फिर इन इश्यूज को पूरी दुनिया तक
journey starts from the ground to the
पहुंचाते हैं। शुरू जमीन से लेकर सफर है
sky.  This art of the pen is peace for the soul.
आसमा का। कलम की ये कला है सुकून है आत्मा
Darkness is the light on the path in life.   He does
का। अंधेरा जिंदगी में राह पर रोशनी है।
n't let me stay with my mother.   I do
मुझे रुकने ना देता है साथ-साथ मां का।
n't talk about age, I don't keep a distance from people,
उम्र की बात ना लोगों से रखती फासला मैं
whatever they say behind my back, today I don't ask
जो पीठ पीछे कहते जो भी कहती आज ना मैं
questions from me, but don't listen to the answers, yes,
सवाल मुझसे करते पर जवाब सुनते नहीं हां
I know a lot, but I will reveal my secrets, when
काफी जानू मैं भी लेकिन खोलूं राजनामा जब
I was five years old, I
मैं पांच साल की थी तब से मैंने डायरी
started writing a diary because I was alone, I didn't have any
लिखना स्टार्ट किया था क्योंकि मैं अकेली
friends and then after that that
थी मेरे दोस्त नहीं थे और फिर उसके बाद वो
thing started coming in the form of art, that
चीज आर्ट फॉर्म में आने लगी वो डायरी
way of writing a diary, that writing poetry, after that
लिखने का तरीका वो पोएट्री लिखना उसके बाद
I started rapping, my father is
मैंने रैप करना स्टार्ट किया मेरे फादर तो
very proud of me, I am his son,
बहुत प्राउड करते हैं उनके लिए बेटा हूं
he always comes to pick me up,
मैं वो हमेशा हमेशा मुझे पिकअप करने आते
whenever the performance is over at night, he does
हैं रात को जब भी परफॉर्मेंस हो खत्म हो
n't come to the performance and I
जाती है परफॉर्मेंस में नहीं आते और मुझे
think it is good, meaning he should
लगता है अच्छा ही है मतलब उन्हें तब तक
not come to the performance till it is not
परफॉर्मेंस में नहीं आना चाहिए मेरी तब तक
too big, till there is
कुछ बहुत ज्यादा बड़ा ना हो तब तक लाखों
no crowd of lakhs, it is the
के भीड़ ना
month of Ramadan right now, meaning
हो अभी रमजान का महीना है मतलब यहां की
more than 70% of the population here
70% से भी ज्यादा पॉपुलेशन फास्ट रोजा
keeps fast, how difficult it would be to
रखती है कितना मुश्किल मुश्किल होगा पूरे
stay without drinking water for the whole day, without eating food, from
दिन बिना पानी पिए बिना खाना खाए रहना
4:00 in the morning to 6:00 in the night, going and
सुबह 4:00 बजे से रात को 6:00 बजे जाके
breaking the fast, it is not easy in this place, we
फास्ट तोड़ना इस जगह में आसान तो नहीं है
break the fast with dates
रोजा खजूर खजूर से तोड़ते हैं
because our profiteering people
क्योंकि हमारे जो प्रॉफिट है ना उनकी पहली
prefer this.  And this is also a superstition,
पसंद है ये और ये सुन्नत भी है
people only know that
लोगों को तो यही खाली पता है कि बस स्लम
in the slums there is only drug addiction, crime,
में सिर्फ नशे होते हैं क्राइम होते हैं
fighting, it is not like that
मारधाड़ ये वो भला धमाका ऐसा नहीं है
but there are a lot of
लेकिन क्योंकि स्लम्स में ना बहुत सारे
talented people in the slums.  Our movies
टैलेंटेड लोग हैं। हमारी मूवीज ना हमें
tell us that there
बताती है कि इन गलियों में बहुत सारे
are and will be lots of gangsters, crime, drugs in these streets.
गैंगस्टर्स, क्राइम, नशे मिलेंगे और
But movies do not tell that
लेकिन मूवीज यह नहीं बताती कि इन्हीं
tuition centres also run in these same streets.
गलियों में ट्यूशन सेंटर्स भी चलते हैं।
One of which is this, which is run by the youth here for the youth here.
जिनमें से एक यह है जो यहीं का यूथ यहां
More than 100 children come to this tuition centre every day.
सेंटर में 100 से भी ज्यादा बच्चे रोज आते
Read with hope.  It is
हैं। आशा के साथ पढ़ते हैं। बच्चों को
important for children to study so that
पढ़ना इसलिए जरूरी है कि आने वाले वक्त
in the future they
में वो अपनी जिंदगी को लेकर अपनी फैमिलीज
can think better about their lives, their families, and their area.  He is helping his own family, his
बेहतर सोच सके। खुद की फैमिली को, खुद के
people and the people in the neighbourhood.  If
लोगों को आसपास अड़ोस पड़ोस के लोगों को
someone is better educated, then
हेल्प कर रहा है। कोई बेहतर पढ़ा लिखा है
I would like my children too to become each other
तो मैं चाहूंगा कि मेरे बच्चे भी एक दूसरे
's strength and not their weakness.   There are
की ताकत बने ना कि कमजोरी बने।
many children here who have very
यहां पे ना बहुत ऐसे बच्चे जिनके बहुत
good talent but they cannot go out
बहुत अच्छा टैलेंट है और वो बाहर अपने
because of their circumstances or because of the people.  Even
हालात की वजह से या फिर लोगों की वजह से
if someone leaves, it is
जा नहीं सकते। अगर कोई चले भी गया इसे ये
suppressed by saying this.  It means that he should
बोल के दबाया जाता है। मतलब ये ऐसे एरिया
come from such an area where there is a lot of violence,
से आए जहां पे है ना बहुत मतलब मारकाट
hashish and marijuana, or he will also keep doing the same thing.
होता है चरस गांजा या फिर ये भी वही करता
So it is not put back.
रहेगा। तो उसको ना पीछे डाला जाता है।
[Music]
[संगीत]
Many of you might have already written in the comments
आप में से कई लोग ना कमेंट्स में ऑलरेडी
that people here are like this.
लिख चुके होंगे कि लोग यहां पे ऐसे ही
These will not change.  So I will
हैं। ये नहीं बदलेंगे। तो मैं उनसे
ask them, do lotuses not grow in insects?
पूछूंगी कि क्या कीट में कमल नहीं उगते?
These children were born here and grew up here.  But if they
ये बच्चे यहीं पे जन्मे यहीं बड़े हुए। पर
still hope for change, then
फिर भी बदलाव की उम्मीद रखते हैं तो हम
why can't we?  Why can't we ask our government and the
क्यों नहीं? हम क्यों नहीं अपनी सरकार से
country whether change is not possible here
देश से पूछ सकते कि क्या यहां बदलाव